בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, Happy Memorial Day. Today's דף daf is פ"א,
Pey-Aleph, but we pick up in the middle of פ"א ע"ב, Pey-Aleph
Amud Bet, and we are dealing with a case where the משנה
mishna teaches that as a general rule you can't bring your תודה
Todah from מעשר שני Maaser Sheni money. The next משנה mishna will
say the key phrase, which is דבר שבחובה אינו בא מן החולין,
Davar she'bechova eino ba min hachulin, something that is an obligatory, an
obligatory sacrifice specifically can only come from חולין hulin money, not from
sanctified money, מעשר שני Maaser Sheni money, unless you explicitly specify. Somehow
by explicitly specifying and saying I am obligating myself in a תודה
Todah from מעשר שני Maaser Sheni money, so you sort of, you
know, stipulate it from the very beginning. Also remember that the קרבן
korban can come from מעשר שני Maaser Sheni money if it's not
an obligation. You can use מעשר שני Maaser Sheni money to bring
a שלמים, Shelamim, we'll see very soon in the גמרא Gemara that
that would be a classic use of מעשר שני Maaser Sheni money,
where you could use מעשר שני Maaser Sheni money to bring a
תודה, Todah, but not to discharge an obligation. So somehow if you
from the very get-go stipulate you're going to use it, that's okay,
and the משנה mishna discusses if you stipulate one thing for the
bread and one thing for the תודה. Todah. So we pick up
here on the middle of פ"א ע"ב, Pey-Aleph Amud Bet,
where it says like this, אמאי, Amai, it's like about there's a
ב bet in parentheses, a רש"י Rashi ב bet with an asterisk
sort of right in the middle, it's about ten lines before the
lines get wide. So it says the following: אמאי, Amai, why when
you say you know I am going to bring a תודה Todah
from what do you call it, from מעשר שני Maaser Sheni money,
excuse me no, אמאי Amai is the case where, I'm sorry just
one second, yes, why when somebody says, we're going back to the
ברייתא Baraita we said at the end of yesterday, when somebody says
I will bring a תודה Todah but I don't want to bring
the bread, I'm going to bring a תודה Todah on the condition
I don't have to bring the bread, it says well you obligated
yourself in a תודה, Todah, we force you to bring the bread.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמאי, Amai, why? It says נדר ופתחו
עמו, Neder u'pitcho imo,
it's a vow with its own opening, meaning that since you said
I want to bring a תודה Todah and not the bread, we
should say you never intended to do the whole thing, so your
vow isn't binding. Why do we say well you take the first
half of your statement, which is you wanted to bring a תודה,
Todah, and once you're bringing a תודה Todah you're forced to bring
the bread? Why don't we say look at the whole statement and
I didn't want to bring only half so I bring nothing? So
that's what it says, why don't we say it's a נדר ופתחו
עמו, Neder u'pitcho imo, a vow with its opening. אמר חזקיה, Amar
Chizkiyah, so חזקיה Chizkiyah says הא מני בית שמאי היא דאמר תפוס
לשון ראשון. Ha mani Beit Shammai hi de'amar tfos lashon rishon. This
is בית שמאי Beit Shammai that says no we do split what
you say, we look at the first half of your statement and
we are not willing to just look at it in totality. This
is in general a position of בית שמאי Beit Shammai that when
it comes to things like נדרים nedarim and הקדש, hekdesh, they are
much more looking at sort of objectively what is done rather than
what is in your mind. So for example בית שמאי Beit Shammai
is also of the opinion that הקדש בטעות hekdesh be-ta'ut is still
הקדש. hekdesh. If you
accidentally sanctified something and you know we find out you didn't mean
to, it doesn't matter. They much more look objectively at what you
say. So it says okay, but you said the words I want
to obligate myself in a נדר, neder, in a תודה, Todah, that
became binding. דתנן, De-tnan, we've taught in a משנה: mishna: הריני נזיר
מן הגרוגרות ומן הדבילה, Hareini nazir min ha-grogrot u'min ha-dveilah, somebody says
I am going to be a נזיר nazir to prevent myself from
eating like figs, you know? So obviously there's no such thing as
a נזיר nazir from figs, a נזיר nazir is about grapes, but
you said the words I am going to be a נזיר. nazir.
Although the end of the sentence you clarified what you were thinking,
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says I don't care what you clarified, you
said the words I am going to be a נזיר. nazir. So
בית שמאי אומרים נזיר, Beit Shammai omerim nazir, you're a נזיר, nazir,
a real נזיר nazir from wine, ובית הלל אומרים אינו נזיר, u'Beit
Hillel omerim eino nazir, you're not, you look at the whole statement.
So therefore this idea that you have to bring the תודה Todah
and you don't look at the whole statement is בית שמאי, Beit
Shammai, that they say those are the words you said, that obligates
you even though in the larger context it's clear that you only
wanted to bring
a תודה Todah without the bread. That's how it's going to בית
שמאי. Beit Shammai. רבי יוחנן אמר אפילו תימא בית הלל, Rabbi Yochanan
amar afilu teima Beit Hillel, it could even be בית הלל. Beit
Hillel. באומר, Be'omer, the person says explicitly, אילו הייתי יודע שאין נודבין
כך לא הייתי נודר כך אלא כך. Ilu hayiti yodea she-ein nodvin
kach lo hayiti noder kach ela kach. Had I realized that I
could not bring a תודה Todah without the bread, had somebody told
me ahead of time hey buddy it's either all or nothing, תודה
Todah with the bread or nothing, then of course I would have
wanted to bring the תודה Todah with the bread. So even though
I said תודה Todah without the bread, that was because I thought
it was possible. Had I realized that wasn't possible then I would
have wanted to bring the תודה Todah with the bread. So that's
what we're saying, which is now of course the question becomes, did
the person literally say those words, oh let me oh let me
explain, you know here's what I really had in mind? Or do
we sort of mean that like we could assume that that's what
a person is thinking? If somebody says I want to be a
נזיר nazir from dates, so we assume that they had a weird
idea of what a נזיר nazir is and it's not like they
really want to stop drinking wine, they want to not eat dates,
they just think you can do it. But if somebody says a
תודה Todah without bread, you know the bread is secondary although of
course as we learned there's tons of bread, but anyway so maybe
it's reasonable to assume that at the end if the person were
to realize you would have to bring the bread, he would of
course want to do that. So it's a little unclear whether we're
saying whether we should interpret this to mean that the person explicitly
clarified what he said, which also raises interesting
questions. It sounds like the Gemara thinks that he explicitly said it
because let's look at the next line. So next line of the
Gemara says like this. So
the Gemara says: ומאי כופין. u-mai kofin. So what does it mean
that now you force him to bring the bread since he's basically
said or we're assuming he said that oh had I realized you
had to do the whole package I would have brought the bread.
So why does it say so you force him to bring the
bread? Presumably he's ready to bring the bread as long as you
just inform him that that's what he has to do. What do
you mean force him? So the Gemara says: דקבעי הדר ביה. d-ka-ba'ei
hadar beih. No, now all of a sudden he's changing his mind.
At the time he said look had I known of course I
would have obligated myself in the bread. Right now I'm no longer
interested in bringing the bread. So I don't want to. So now
we say sort of tough luck. Okay, so the fact that it
says like he's changing his mind הדר ביה hadar beih etcetera sounds
like initially he explicitly said oh yeah had I realized then I
would have obligated myself in the bread too and now says but
you know now I'm no longer interested and we say tough luck
now you're no longer interested now we're going to force you. Okay
but again I would rather assume that rather than him saying explicitly
it's reasonable to say you know that in any time when we
sort of have to this is always the tricky part of נדרים
Nedarim I mean we're not learning נדרים Nedarim but you know where
we care not just about what a person said like בית שמאי
Beit Shammai but we also care what a person is thinking is
how do you get a handle on exactly what they're thinking? You
know and how do you get a handle like in this case
where okay he was thinking the תודה todah without the bread but
did he did he mean only that like that or nothing or
did he sort of mean you know if he could do it
without the bread he wants it without the bread but otherwise he'd
be prepared to do the whole תודה? todah? You know how much
is it all one big package or not and sometimes we have
to sort of try to evaluate that. Okay so that's the end
of that discussion. Now we get back to our main focus about
the about whether it comes from מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni money or
not. Let's take a look. תא שמע. ta shema. Come here. האומר
הרי עלי תודה בלא לחם
וזבח בלא ha-omer harei alai todah belo lechem ve-zevach belo oh I'm
sorry we're still wrapping up this previous discussion האומר הרי עלי תודה
בלא לחם וזבח בלא נסכים ha-omer harei alai todah belo lechem ve-zevach
belo nesachim I am going to bring a תודה todah without bread
or a sacrifice without the נסכים. nesachim. ואמרו לו ve-amru lo and
we said to him הביא תודה ולחמה וזבח ונסכים havei todah ve-lachmah
ve-zevach ve-nesachim bring the תודה todah with its bread
no
tough you don't have that choice you said תודה todah you gotta
bring it with its bread or bring the you said sacrifice you
have to bring it with the נסכים nesachim you do not have
the choice וזבח ונסכים ve-zevach ve-nesachim והוא אומר ve-hu omer he said
back אילו הייתי יודע שכן ilu hayiti yodei'a sheken had I known
you would have forced me to bring
everything לא הייתי נודר lo hayiti noder then I would never have
taken the vow to bring the to the תודה todah in the
first place I would never have taken the vow to bring the
sacrifice in the first place I want to do all or nothing
I mean not all or nothing I want to do it just
halfway some or nothing I want to do it halfway and if
you don't let me do it halfway I don't want to do
it at all. Exactly. So so it says כופין אותו kofin oto
you force him to bring the whole thing because he already said
he wants to bring a תודה todah ואומר לו ve-omer lo and
you say to him שמור ושמעת shemor ve-shama'ta observe and listen. We'll
talk in a minute what that פסוק pasuk is used for. Right
so anyway okay so anyway right so here you see that he
explicitly says I wanted to do half and we ignore that. So
בשלמא לחזקיה ניחא bi-shlama le-Chizkiyah nicha חזקיה Chizkiyah said that it's going
to בית שמאי Beit Shammai that says we really don't care what
you were thinking we only go by what you said. So you
said תודה todah that obligates you even though you only wanted to
bring half tough luck. That makes sense. אלא לרבי יוחנן ela le-Rabbi
Yochanan רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said that we want that we were
trying to explain this according to בית הלל. Beit Hillel. Now בית
הלל Beit Hillel is concerned with what you were thinking. So according
to בית הלל Beit Hillel since he only wanted to do half
why should we just say that nothing takes place? Why should we
say that no you already obligated yourself in a תודה? todah? Says
the Gemara: אמר לך רבי יוחנן הא ודאי בית שמאי היא. amar
lach Rabbi Yochanan ha vadai Beit Shammai hi. No no no look
that ברייתא braita clearly is בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. I was trying
to explain the previous ברייתא. braita. So basically what you have is
that you know רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and חזקיה Chizkiyah don't disagree
according to the debate of בית שמאי בית הלל. Beit Shammai Beit
Hillel. The only question is how they interpret the different ברייתות. braitot.
But everybody agrees that according to בית שמאי Beit Shammai even if
you're thinking one thing you're sort of trapped by your words. So
if you said I'm going to be a נזיר nazir from dates
doesn't matter there's no such thing as a נזיר nazir from dates
you said the word נזיר nazir out of your mouth boom you
became a נזיר. nazir. Or you said I want to bring a
תודה todah without bread and that's the only way I'll bring the
תודה todah is if it's without bread too bad you said the
word תודה todah boom you obligated in a תודה todah you don't
look at the whole context. Or בית הלל Beit Hillel says you
look at the whole context and therefore you would not if that's
the only thing you wanted to do then it would not by
the נזיר nazir be binding. The question is by the תודה todah
because because since by the תודה todah maybe you said or it's
reasonable to assume by the תודה todah that unless you state explicitly
otherwise maybe you would be prepared to bring the whole thing if
you don't have the the opportunity you don't have the ability to
do it halfway. Now we're just going to
end same thing from the נזיר nazir though.
Because by the נזיר nazir clearly well first of all the question
is whether you read the Gemara that he explicitly said he's prepared
to do the whole thing or whether we're assuming that he'd be
prepared. But I'd rather read it assuming it even though there's a
big difference. Somebody who says a נזיר nazir from dates has in
his mind that I don't want to eat dates right does not
have it in his mind like oh you know oh if you
tell me that there's no such thing then I'll want to be
a נזיר nazir and not drink wine. They're completely different things. Okay
if you say that I basically want to bring the תודה todah
oh but without
the bread.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara ends with this שמור ושמעתא.
Shamor Veshamata. מאי שמור ושמעתא? Mai Shamor Veshamata? אמר אביי: Amar Abaye:
שמור, Shamor,
observe what you said, הדא תודה, Hadei Toda, you said you'll bring
the תודה, Toda, bring the תודה. Toda. ושמעתא, Veshamata, and sort of
listen, I guess listen to not what you said but to what
the תורה Torah demands, והדא לחמא, Vehadei Lahma, and bring the bread
that goes with it. So that's what you say back to him.
רבא אמר: Rava Amar: רבא Rava says שמור, Shamor, observe הדא תודה
ולחמא, Hadei Toda Velahma, bring the תודה Toda with its bread, that's
the way the תורה Torah says to bring it, so do what
the תורה Torah says. So what's
ושמעתא? Veshamata? שלא תרגיל לעתיד לבא, Shelo Teragil Le'atid Lavo, but pay
attention that don't get yourself into these situations in the future like,
you know, understand what the laws are so you don't try to
make stipulations which are not, you know, able to be satisfied anyway
in the first place. Okay, so that's just a nice way to
explain the end of that ברייתא. Baraisa. Okay, where was I? Okay,
היא ולחמה מן המעשר. Hi Velahma Min Hama'aser. Now finally
back to back to what back to the משנה. Mishna. You see
on the little side it says פיסקא היא, Piska Hi, which means
basically that like we're going back to you know there should be
the two dots, we're going back to the משנה. Mishna. היא ולחמה
מן המעשר, Hi Velahma Min Hama'aser, if somebody says I obligate myself
to bring a תודה Toda but I am stipulating from the very
outset that I can bring it from the מעשר. Ma'aser. Although normally
as we'll see in the next משנה, Mishna, you cannot bring a
דבר שבחובה מן המעשר, Davar Shebechova Min Hama'aser, you cannot you only
have to bring it מן החולין, Min Hachulin, obligatory
obligations of sacrifices you cannot use your מעשר Ma'aser money for. Nevertheless,
if you say explicitly that's what you're going to do, then somehow
that's a stipulation from the outset and that is allowed. Because again
remember I said this before, if you did not take it as
a personal obligation you just used מעשר Ma'aser money to buy a
קרבן, Korban, to buy שלמים Shelamim or תודה, Toda, that would be
okay. So if you stipulate from the outset that you are obligating
yourself but with the condition or with the stipulation that you know
you will be able to satisfy this with מעשר Ma'aser money, that
is allowed. Okay, so היא ולחמה מן המעשר, Hi Velahma Min Hama'aser,
if I'm going to bring if you say I obligate myself a
תודה Toda and its bread from מעשר, Ma'aser, יביא, Yavi, you can
go ahead and do it or you should bring it. So the
גמרא Gemara says: יביא? Yavi? לא סגי דלא מייתי? Lo Sagi Delo
Meisi? You must bring? What? There's you know meaning are you לא
סגי Lo Sagi means I guess not enough that you would not
bring? Meaning are you required to use מעשר Ma'aser money? You know
you don't have to use מעשר Ma'aser money. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, רב פפא ורב חסדא אמרי, Rav Papa VeRav Chisda Amri,
no, it doesn't mean you must bring from מעשר Ma'aser money. You're
allowing yourself to use מעשר Ma'aser money. It means רצה מייתי, Ratzah
Meivi, if you want to you can now use מעשר Ma'aser money
because you stipulated that explicitly. לא רצה לא מייתי, Lo Ratzah Lo
Meivi, if you don't want to now you're you want to use
חולין Chulin money, so לא יביא, Lo Yavi, don't use מעשר Ma'aser
money. Okay, fine.
But you explicitly said I want to bring it from מעשר Ma'aser
money. Why isn't this an obligation then?
No, I'm not מחייב Mechayev myself. I'm saying that that's the way
it's understanding. Meaning I suppose you could read that משנה Mishna I
mean to make a נדר, Neder, you can make a נדר Neder
whatever you want. Right. But yeah, but it's understanding which is I
think reasonable that since there's generally a restriction of using מעשר Ma'aser
money, when you say I'm going to
bring I obligate myself in a תודה Toda to be able to
from even if that's the question if you say to come from
מעשר Ma'aser money, we're going to read it meaning to allow to
be able to come from מעשר Ma'aser money.
Or maybe it's the opposite. Meaning meaning like you know you you're
you want to be you want to cheap out a little bit.
You know you know you kind of have to bring a תודה
Toda anyway and you know what I have all this מעשר Ma'aser
money, what am I going to do with it? It's going to
go to waste if I don't use it. You know so I
might as well bring my תודה Toda from it. So it means
that you know I really want to use the מעשר Ma'aser money
from it.
I know, but the so it's true, you know, you could look
here's part of the problem as well is that there's a difference
between a נדר Neder and a שבועה, Shevua, meaning a נדר Neder
creates a you know I can't really obligate myself the it gets
a little complicated, it gets into sort of נדרים, Nedarim, but I
really can't obligate myself a personal obligation to do something through a
נדר. Neder. A נדר Neder sort of creates a status. So I
can make a vow to sanctify an animal. I can make a
נדר Neder to obligate myself to bring a קרבן Korban but that's
because תורה Torah sort of recognizes that as a status of being
חייב Chayav in a קרבן. Korban. So I can create that reality
through a vow. I can't if I wanted to say I will
only use my מעשר Ma'aser money to buy my whatever, I can
really only do that through a שבועה. Shevua. שבועה Shevua relates to
actions not to statuses. So it really is like a mixing of
a genre and therefore we basically understand that what it means is
I'm obligating myself but with the condition that the obligation I should
be allowed to satisfy that obligation you know in the following way.
And that's how the גמרא Gemara is choosing to read it.
He chose the wrong words and you really meant to say שבועה.
Shevua.
No, because then you wouldn't have a חיוב. Chiyuv. No, I don't
the anyway okay. I that's what I think anyway but it's a
good question. Right? Why are we choosing to read it as an
option rather than rather than as a חיוב? Chiyuv? It might be
like I'm saying part of the technicality of how נדרים Nedarim work,
it also just might be part of the psychology. That yes, the
person is trying to go on the cheap but trying to go
on the cheap means you want to give yourself that option not
you want to require yourself to go on the cheap. So that's
how the גמרא Gemara is choosing to read it. Okay. Now we
go to the last line of the משנה Mishna which is the
following:
which is ולא יביא מחיטי מעשר שני. Velo Yavi Meichitei Ma'aser Sheni.
Now now that I have allowed myself to buy a to get
a תודה Toda from מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni money, don't bring from
the wheat of מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni. Don't make the תודה todah
bread some actual grain of מעשר שני, maiser sheni, the stuff that
actually grew and was separated off as מעשר שני. maiser sheni.
אלא ממעות מעשר שני. Ela mimos maiser sheni. What you do is
after you transfer the מעשר שני maiser sheni to money, which is
what classically people would do to then bring the money to ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, then you could use the money to buy תודה todah and
its bread. But don't actually use the grain itself to make the
תודה. todah. Now that seems to be, we'll see in a minute
that the גמרא's Gemara going to learn it out, but that seems
to be part of the challenge here seems to be like one
idea's like doing something on the cheap, sort of trying to satisfy
your obligations with something that's supposed to be used for something else.
The other is a concern of almost
of obfuscating thing's identity, doubling up the identity of something. So that
seems to be part of the challenge. Now that's not completely true
because you can use מעשר שני maiser sheni money, you can use
מעשר שני maiser sheni money to buy a תודה todah if you
didn't take an obligation, you can use it to buy your שלמים.
shlomim. We're going to see in a minute that almost a traditional
use of מעשר שני maiser sheni money is to buy a שלמים.
shlomim. But there that's not the מעשר שני maiser sheni itself, that's
just the קדושה kedusha of the מעשר שני maiser sheni on the
money and the goal there is to buy something.
So you're buying something that also has this קדושה, kedusha, it's a
שלמים shlomim or whatever it has, but it's not the מעשר שני
maiser sheni per se. To take something which is both מעשר שני
maiser sheni per se, the grain that grew, and to turn it
into bread of a תודה, todah, that is seen as somewhat of
a compromise of its original identity.
I think that'd be nice.
Right. Well, the גמרא Gemara thinks it's nice too, but it's not
the original thing. If it's some of the original thing, that's somehow
the גמרא Gemara sees as some degree of a compromise. I don't
get it exactly, but that's the way the גמרא...
Gemara... I would have thought this whole thing about ממעט זמן אכילה
mema'et zman achila like we have before. In other words, in מעשר
שני maiser sheni I have, I can
eat it for a whole
long time, and if I make
it into a תודה todah I can only eat it for... that's
an interesting I don't know if we have a concept of ממעט
זמן אכילה mema'et zman achila by things that are not קרבנות. korbanos.
It's an interesting question whether we ever say it by מעשר שני.
maiser sheni. We certainly... hmm...
that's an interesting question. I'd have to check that. Okay, but the
גמרא Gemara doesn't raise it here, just uses a פסוק pasuk as
we'll see. But right, but yeah again, yesterday you were talking about
a קרבן, korban, here you're talking about a non-קרבן. korban. Let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: ולא יביא מחטי
מעשר שני אלא ממעות מעשר שני, v'lo yavi mechitei maiser sheni ela
mimos maiser sheni, מעשר שני maiser sheni money. רב נחמן ורב חסדא
דאמרי תרווייהו: Rav Nachman v'Rav Chisda d'amri tarvaihu: לא שנו אלא מחטי
מעשר שני. lo shanu ela mechitei maiser sheni. You can't use the
grain of מעשר שני. maiser sheni. אבל מחטי הלקוחות ממעות מעשר שני
יביא. aval mechitei ha-lekuchos mimos maiser sheni yavi. You used your מעשר
שני maiser sheni money to buy grain or flour, then you use
that grain or flour that again is like not the original stuff
that grew, that you can make into your תודה todah bread, which
would seem like obvious. How else are you supposed to get your
תודה todah bread with your מעשר שני maiser sheni money if you're
not going to buy grain or flour? So we'll see in a
minute.
That
יביא. yavi.
יתיב רבי ירמיה קמיה
דרבי זירא.
yativ
Rabbi Yirmeyah kamei d'Rabbi Zeira.
So רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeyah was sitting in front of רבי זירא.
Rabbi Zeira. יתיב וקאמר: yativ v'ka'amar: לא שנו אלא מחטי מעשר שני.
lo shanu ela mechitei maiser sheni. Well, the same thing. We're only
talking about that you can't use the actual grain of מעשר שני.
maiser sheni. אבל מחטי הלקוחות במעות מעשר שני יביא. aval mechitei ha-lekuchos
bimos maiser sheni yavi. But from grain that's purchased with מעשר שני
maiser sheni money, that you can bring. אמר ליה. amar lei. So
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira who said back to
רבי ירמיה: Rabbi Yirmeyah: רבי אתה אומר כן? rabbi ata omer ken?
Do you really say this?
אני אומר. ani omer. I say: אפילו מחטי הלקוחות במעות מעשר שני
לא יביא. afilu mechitei ha-lekuchos bimos maiser sheni lo yavi. You can't
even make your תודה todah bread
from grain that was bought with מעשר שני. maiser sheni. Now, of
course, if you're not doing that, how are you bringing your תודה
todah bread from מעשר שני maiser sheni money? So as we'll see,
it's not really even explicit in the גמרא, Gemara, it's implicit. The
point is that you use the money to buy bread. Don't use
the money to buy wheat. If you're going to use your מעשר
שני maiser sheni money to buy תודה todah bread in the case
where you're allowed, where you stipulate that you're allowed in the משנה,
Mishnah, don't buy wheat with it or flour. Don't buy wheat with
it, maybe buy the bread itself. Now what's the difference? Or maybe
buy flour. So we're going to see in a minute, it seems
a little strange. Let's see what the difference is.
Was everybody actually making these תודה todah breads for sale?
Apparently, which is a big surprise, because one thing we said before,
who sifts the flour? Can you buy flour through some third party?
But here of course, by the way, the תודה todah bread itself,
there's a question of do you make it in a כלי שרת?
kli shares? If you made it in a כלי שרת, kli shares,
do you have to make it in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
not in the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Very, very.
And you have this leaner thing because if someone buys yours today...
No, no. The תודה todah bread, because תודה todah is linked to
the קרבן, korban, there it doesn't become קדוש kadosh until the שחיטת
הזבח. shchitas hazavach. But nevertheless, the whole thing is very strange. Let's
see what his reason is also that who really cares if it's
difference if once you're buying it whether you're buying wheat or flour
or bread? So let's take a look. ואימא טעמי דידי ואימא טעמי
דידך. v'eima ta'amei didi v'eima ta'amei didach. I'll tell you my reason
and I'll tell you your reason.
This was רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira talking to רבי ירמיה. Rabbi Yirmeyah.
It's funny that he calls him
רבי. rabbi. Maybe they were colleagues but used it as an
honorific. Exactly. So I'll tell you your reason and I'll tell you
my reason. אימא טעמי דידך. eima ta'amei didach. Let me explain to
you what obviously your reasoning is. תודה מהיכא קא ילפת לה? todah
me-heicha ka yalfat lah?
Where do you learn out a תודה? todah? Meaning where do you
learn out that you can use that you can use מעשר ma'aser
money to buy a תודה? toda? משלמים, Mishlamim, from שלמים, Shelamim, because
we know you can use מעשר ma'aser money to buy שלמים. Shelamim.
Again, assuming you're not exempting yourself from any obligation, just straight to
use the money to buy a שלמים Shelamim or to buy a
תודה. toda. How do you know that? שלמים שם שם ממעשר. Shelamim
sham sham mima'aser. There's a גזירה שוה gezeira shava to מעשר. ma'aser.
What does it say by שלמים? Shelamim? It says by שלמים, Shelamim,
רש"י Rashi quotes it here, it says, ואכלת שם, veachalta sham, that
you should and it says by מעשר, ma'aser, ונתת בכסף בידך ואכלת
שם לפני ה' אלקיך. venatata bakesef beyadecha veachalta sham lifnei Hashem Elokecha.
So there's a גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. Now I want to stop
for a minute and say something about this גזירה שוה. gezeira shava.
They both talk about eating in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Now we're saying this
is where you learn that you can use מעשר שני ma'aser sheni
money to buy שלמים Shelamim because you know, you might think that
even if it's not getting myself out of an obligation, maybe מעשר
שני ma'aser sheni money should be used to buy, you know, normal
unsanctified thing. Maybe I can't double it up as a קרבן. korban.
But here we say we learn from this גזירה שוה gezeira shava
you're allowed.
Allowed or should.
Right. That's what we're going to see in a minute. What we're
going to see in a minute is even more than that. It's
not explicit in this גמרא, Gemara, but it is in other in
משניות mishnayot in מעשר שני ma'aser sheni that you were if you
were going to buy meat, you're expected to buy a שלמים Shelamim
with your מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money. You were not supposed to
buy meat as בשר תאוה, basar ta'avah, as normal meat to eat
without a קרבן, korban, you were supposed to bring a שלמים Shelamim
with your מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money. Why?
But then you give it to the, you know, also it's a
מצוה mitzvah to give it to the poor and all that, right?
Or?
שלמים? Shelamim? No. כהנים Kohanim get a piece of it. You don't
give שלמים Shelamim to the poor.
Doesn't it say ונתתה ללוי venatetah lalevi and all that or?
By שלמים? Shelamim? No, by מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni.
Yeah, that's what I'm saying. Oh, so okay, but who cares?
Meaning, give them normal meat. Why do you have to give them
שלמים Shelamim meat?
Well, because because that's like a whole part of what you do
with the קרבנות. korbanot.
Well, no, I think it's more than that. I think it's more
simple than that. I think the point is is what's the idea
of מעשר שני? ma'aser sheni? The whole idea of מעשר שני ma'aser
sheni is is that it forces you to come to ירושלים Yerushalayim
and as it says, ואכלת שם לפני ה' אלקיך ושמחת בכל הטוב,
veachalta sham lifnei Hashem Elokecha vesamachta bechol hatov, that you're sort of,
you know, you are once again going into the center of קדושה,
kedusha, ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, although you don't even
have to walk into the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash with your מעשר
שני, ma'aser sheni, you're just going to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But nevertheless, the
תורה Torah frames it as לפני ה' אלקיך. lifnei Hashem Elokecha. So
there's a way in which, you know, your consumption and your eating
of the produce, we're not forcing you to give it away, like
we do by other מעשרות, ma'asrot, you get to eat it yourself,
but it's putting it in a whole religious context. Well, the whole
idea of the שלמים Shelamim of ואכלת שם ושמחת veachalta sham vesamachta
and they're both tied with the concept of שמחה simcha is the
idea that this is a type of an eating that's in the
presence of God and that evokes a sense of שמחה simcha and
joy and wholeness because it's in communion with God and so on.
So there's a very strong conflation of the goals of מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni and the goal of eating שלמים, Shelamim, that ואכלת שם,
achalta sham, that eating in the presence of God. So that's why
I think it's not just allowed, right, but it's specifically is, you
know, is sort of encouraged, if you're going to eat meat, to
turn it into a שלמים. Shelamim. So that's what we say by
מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. And therefore תודה Toda is a type of
a שלמים, Shelamim, so you're allowed to also use מעשר שני ma'aser
sheni money to buy a תודה. Toda. That allows you to tell
you מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money can go towards a תודה. Toda.
Okay, now we're going to get to the bread. ממעשר Mima'aser ומנא,
umina, from that, you will say מה שלמים אין גופן מעשר, mah
Shelamim ein gufan ma'aser, by the same way the שלמים Shelamim obviously
can never are never מעשר ma'aser itself, you never grow a cow
that's מעשר, ma'aser, okay, because right, because מעשר ma'aser is only stuff
that grows from the ground, is only grain. מעשר שני, Ma'aser sheni,
right but that's good, cute, but that's not the מעשר ma'aser we're
talking about, not מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. אף תודה נמי אין גופה
מעשר. Af Toda nami ein gufah ma'aser. So anything that you are
so when you can use מעשר ma'aser for a שלמים Shelamim or
תודה, Toda, it's it has to be like the way you use
מעשר ma'aser for a שלמים. Shelamim. It cannot be the מעשר ma'aser
itself, because the מעשר ma'aser itself would never be a שלמים. Shelamim.
So therefore when you're making a תודה, Toda, it cannot be the
מעשר ma'aser itself. And therefore you can't use the grain itself, you
have to take the כסף, kesef, the money of the מעשר ma'aser
and from that buy grain, but it can't be the grain itself.
Okay, so that's a very reasonable position and as I said conceptually
what it's about, it's that somehow we'd sort of compromise the identity
to take the very מעשר ma'aser itself and to now reuse that
as a type of לחמי תודה, lachmei toda, you lose its original
status. If you're just taking קדושת מעשר, kedushas ma'aser, it's an appropriate
use for מעשר ma'aser funds, for מעשר שני ma'aser sheni funds, but
it would compromise the thing itself. That's the way I see it.
I don't think קל וחומר. kal vachomer. I know. So okay, but
at least I'm trying to explain what I have, okay, I'm not
making it up out of scratch. Alright, anyway, that's your position, that
you cannot use the grain itself for the bread of the תודה.
Toda. תודה נמי אין גופה מעשר, Toda nami ein gufah ma'aser, והני
חטים הלקוחות במעות מעשר שני, vehani chitim halekuchos bema'os ma'aser sheni, and
if
you use the מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money to buy or to
buy wheat, נמי אין גופן מעשר, nami ein gufan ma'aser,
so it's not the so you're not buying the stuff that was
originally מעשר, ma'aser, you're you're using מעשר ma'aser money to purchase it
and therefore you're okay. That's your position, that you can't use the
wheat itself that was מעשר ma'aser but you can purchase wheat and
make it out of the bread of the תודה. Toda. That's your
reason. אימא טעמי דדידי, Eima tamei dididi, now let me explain to
you my reason. תודה מהיכא קא יפינן לה, Toda meheicha kayafinan lei,
same thing. Where do you know that you can use מעשר ma'aser
money? to buy a תודה Toda משלמים, mishlamim, from a שלמים. shelamim.
ושלמים שם שם ממעשר, Veshelamim shama shama mimaaser,
and שלמים shelamim we learn out from מעשר maaser that you can
make, that you can, that you can use מעשר maaser money to
buy a שלמים. shelamim. מה שלמים אין מן מעשר אף תודה אין
מן מעשר. Mah shelamim ein min maaser af toda ein min maaser.
It's not just that שלמים shelamim is not מעשר maaser itself. שלמים
shelamim meat is never a type of a thing that ever could
be מעשר. maaser. Meat would never be מעשר. maaser. So therefore when
you are going to use your, when you're going to bring your
תודה, toda, you can only bring your תודה toda from things that
never would have been מעשר. maaser. And therefore you can't bring your
תודה toda from wheat because wheat would have been מעשר. maaser. לאסוקי
חטים לקוחות ממעשר שני, Le'asukei chitim lekuchos mimaaser sheni,
therefore I will not let you use wheat even though it was
not originally מעשר. maaser. I won't let you use wheat that you're
purchasing with מעשר maaser money to make the bread, דמין מעשר נינהו,
demin maasernin hu, because wheat is at least a type of thing
that could be מעשר. maaser. So therefore what are you supposed to,
how are you supposed to make your bread with מעשר maaser money?
You're not supposed to buy the wheat, says רש"י, Rashi, you're supposed
to buy the bread itself. Although I wonder because again it did
bother me, there's all these questions about right, the, how about the
flour? At least the flour is not in its original state. Right,
because it did bother me because all these assumptions about like where
you're doing making the bread and so on. All of a sudden
we have to assume that somebody else is making even the bread
for you. So maybe the flour would be, would be okay. But
again it's a very bizarre position one must say. Like we had
a hard enough time explaining why you can't use the original מעשר
maaser to make תודה toda bread. And there you could say well
if it's the original thing, you're totally like it's supposed to be
מעשר maaser and you're totally totally losing its identity by becoming bread
of תודה. toda. Okay, but to say that because in theory wheat
could have been מעשר, maaser, therefore I'm not allowed to use my
מעשר maaser money to purchase it for the sake of a תודה,
toda, that's very bizarre. Okay, that's that debate. Now we, now we
go on with how you can sort of issues about doubling up.
Let's take a look. אמר רבי אמי, Amar Rabbi Ammi, המתפיס מעות
מעשר שני לשלמים לא קנו שלמים.
hamatpis maos maaser sheni leshelamim
lo kanu shelamim. Now, you have your מעשר maaser money. Now we
just got through saying, what can I use my מעשר maaser money
to do? To go ahead and to buy a שלמים shelamim or
to buy a תודה, toda, again assuming I'm not exempting myself from
an obligation. So I can use the money to buy a שלמים
shelamim or to buy an animal and then I'll take the animal
and sanctify it as שלמים. shelamim. But if I try to actually
sanctify the money itself, this is מעשר שני maaser sheni money and
I try to say I am dedicating that money for שלמים, shelamim,
I am sanctifying it with קדושת שלמים, kedushas shelamim, and now I'm
going to use it to buy a שלמים, shelamim, that doesn't work.
Okay, which is strange, right? It seems like in the end it's
all the same point, you're going to use the money for the
שלמים, shelamim, so let's take a look at what he says. לא
קנו שלמים, Lo kanu shelamim, they did not, the שלמים shelamim didn't
acquire it or it didn't get the קדושה kedusha of שלמים. shelamim.
מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? You can't do, yeah,
the קדושה kedusha didn't hold. So now you're still free to use
the money however you want to. Okay, which is again bizarre. You
can use the money to buy an animal and that animal becomes
your שלמים, shelamim, but I can't actually sanctify the money with קדושת
שלמים. kedushas shelamim. If I had normal money I could. I could
take out a thousand dollars or five hundred dollars or whatever and
I sanctify it with קדושת שלמים kedushas shelamim and now I have
to use it for a שלמים. shelamim. But I can't do that
with my מעשר maaser money. Why not? לא קנו שלמים. Lo kanu
shelamim. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama why? דלא אלימא קדושת השלמים למיחל קדושת
מעשר שני. delo alima kedushas hashelamim lemeichel kedushas maaser sheni. Well that
wasn't so explanatory. The sanctity of the שלמים shelamim is not strong
enough, I, that's what I'm going to say. But let's just translate
the words: the sanctity of the שלמים shelamim is not strong enough
to take effect on top of the sanctity of the מעשר שני.
maaser sheni. Now the way I would explain it is very similar
to what I said before about using the wheat. That you're really
sort of compromising the identity. If you think about it, it's a
very nice analogy. The same way the wheat that actually was מעשר
שני maaser sheni should not now become a תודה toda itself because
this is the original sort of wheat so it loses its identity
if it becomes לחמי תודה. lachmei toda. This is money of מעשר
שני. maaser sheni. To make it into שלמים shelamim money changes its
identity. It really is competing with its very fundamental identity. To take
the money as money of מעשר שני, maaser sheni, buy an animal,
so now it's not money of מעשר שני, maaser sheni, now it's
an animal, okay, that's קדושת מעשר שני kedushas maaser sheni or whatever,
but now I can also make it into a שלמים, shelamim, that's
not really sort of competing with its identity. But money of מעשר
שני maaser sheni has a very much defined, here's money, here's what
you're supposed to do with it. You're supposed to use it towards
מעשר שני maaser sheni ends. And now I am redefining sort of,
you know, what type of money it is. That seems to be
the issue here. You could even say maybe a little bit differently,
I think רש"י Rashi also suggests that you're also, but I think
what I'm about to say is really an expression of my first
point, that you're limiting its, you know, you're limiting its scope. מעשר
שני Maaser sheni money you're supposed to be able to use בכל
אשר תאוה נפשך, bechol asher te'aveh nafshecha, whatever you want.
And now I'm saying, and now I'm saying,
oh,
I'm not going to use it for whatever I want. I'm going
to limit the ability of this money and it can only be
used for one thing. So I am sort of changing its, you
know, its power as מעשר שני maaser sheni money. As opposed to
when I actually purchase something with it, then I say oh, this
thing I want to turn into a שלמים, shelamim, that I am
entitled to do. But when as money it's supposed to have the
ability to be used for whatever I want. Okay, so that you're
not allowed to do. So now the גמרא Gemara will question this.
מיתיבי
*Meitivei*, I'll ask you on this, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, הלוקח
חיה *Haloke'ach Chayah*, here's the idea that you're supposed to only be
using it for שלמים Shlamim, *Shlamim* or at least if you're buying
animals that can be brought as שלמים Shlamim. *Shlamim*, you're supposed to
use it for שלמים Shlamim *Shlamim*. הלוקח חיה לזבחי שלמים Shlamim *Haloke'ach
chayah le'zivchei shlamim*. The משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* says
that
if you are purchasing a חיה *chayah*, let's say a deer, and
you're saying I'm using my מעשר שני Maaser Sheini, *Ma'aser Sheni* money
to buy this deer and I'm going to bring it as a
שלמים Shlamim *Shlamim*. Of course, that's impossible. You cannot bring a שלמים
Shlamim *Shlamim* out of a חיה *chayah*. You can only bring it
out of a בהמה beheima *behemah*. Okay, so you just have some
weird ideas in your head. ובהמה לבשר תאוה *U'vehemah levasar ta'avah*, or
I'm buying this cow for meat, for steaks, that's what I'm doing
with my מעשר שני Maaser Sheini *Ma'aser Sheni* money. Now, both of
these are seen as unusual usages of the מעשר שני Maaser Sheini
*Ma'aser Sheni* money because the implicit, which is the other משנה mishna
*Mishnah* there, is that the proper use is what? To use it
either for if you want to just סתם *stam* eat meat and
not bring it as a קורבן *korban*, so then you buy a
חיה *chayah*. You buy a deer for steaks. Okay, because you can't
bring that as a קורבן *korban*. And if you want to bring
a בהמה *behemah*, then you're supposed to bring it for a שלמים
Shlamim *Shlamim*. That's what you're supposed to do with your מעשר שני
Maaser Sheini *Ma'aser Sheni* money. You, however, reversed it. You tried to
buy a cow for steaks and a deer for שלמים Shlamim *Shlamim*.
So what does the משנה mishna. *Mishnah* say? If I want to
buy a deer for steaks, that's okay.
Yes, deer for steaks is okay and a cow for שלמים shelamim.
*Shlamim* is okay, but you reversed it. So what does the משנה
mishna *Mishnah* say?
Wait, a cow for שלמים shelamim, *Shlamim* is okay because that's what
we've been talking about.
Right, right, correct. A deer for steaks is also okay because you
don't have an option of bringing a deer for שלמים shelamim, *Shlamim*,
so we didn't have a problem with that.
But you'd say just don't buy the deer and
just bring a שלמים shelamim. *Shlamim*. Yeah, I know, but okay, that
חז"ל *Chazal* did not have a problem with. Okay, so anyway, ובהמה
לבשר תאוה *U'vehemah levasar ta'avah*, לא יצא העור לחולין lo yatza ha-or
l'chullin *lo yatza ha'or lechulin*. The skin does not become desanctified. Now,
what does that mean? It means that there's a general principle: can
I use my מעשר שני Maaser Sheini *Ma'aser Sheni* money to buy
wine? Well, why not? Well, you see, wine comes in a bottle.
And let's say of the ten dollar cost of the wine, one
dollar is going towards the bottle. Okay, so have I now used
my מעשר שני Maaser Sheini *Ma'aser Sheni* money to buy non-food? So
the הלכה *Halachah* is that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
has to keep the wine in something.
Well, obviously! Maybe I have to pay nine dollars of the מעשר
שני Maaser Sheini *Ma'aser Sheni* money and one dollar out of my
pocket. So no, so we don't require that, so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* elsewhere whatever learns that out, you know, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
learns out from a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, whatever, I think בכל אשר
תאוה *bechol asher te'aveh*, however it learns out, that if it's sort
of, you know, incorporated in the whole cost, it's okay that the
money goes for that as well. And presumably what also happens is
not only can I use my ten dollars for the bottle of
wine, but now the bottle of wine I don't have to somehow
resell and use the proceeds for more מעשר maaser *Ma'aser* purchases. Now
I can just use this bottle of wine for whatever I want.
So by analogy or by the same application of the same principle,
if I buy a בהמה *behemah*, right, some of the cost goes
towards the skin, the leather, maybe it's only a small part, but
nevertheless, what after I buy this בהמה *behemah* and I eat the
meat or whatever, I'm allowed to use the leather for whatever I
want, I don't have to treat it anymore as מעשר שני Maaser
Sheini *Ma'aser Sheni* money. That יצא העור לחולין *yatza ha'or lechulin*. Now,
that is only when the way in which you use the money
was an acceptable way, was a way in which was seen as
the normal way because again, you know, you could let's say also
try to, sort of, game the system. Let's say you sort of
say Michael has this gorgeous vase to sell and I have all
this מעשר שני Maaser Sheini, *Ma'aser Sheni* money, so what I'm going
to say to Michael is, tell you what, why not sell me
put some apple juice in that vase and then sell me the
apple juice for a hundred dollars, right? So I'm tricking, right, I'm
not really buying the apple juice. So the idea of יצא לחולין
*yatza lechulin* is when this is the normal type of a purchase.
So now, in this case where you are doing what we don't
approve of is considered to be a non-normal type of a purpose
because it's not the way normal people did it once they're following
the rules. So you buying a חיה *chayah* for שלמים shelamim *Shlamim*,
which is crazy, or buying a בהמה *behemah* for בשר תאוה basar
taava, *basar ta'avah*, is seen as non-normal uses of מעשר שני Maaser
Sheini *Ma'aser Sheni*, and therefore you do not get the benefit of
saying that you get the עור *or* for, you know, the עור
*or* is freed from the מעשר שני Maaser Sheini *Ma'aser Sheni* restrictions.
So as a result, what do you have to do now? You
have to now sell the leather and you use the proceeds of
that leather in order to buy more מעשר שני Maaser Sheini? *Ma'aser
Sheni* products, more food products that you'll eat in ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim*.
Is that not another way of seeing that it doesn't work? Meaning
it does work but you just have to add more?
It does work because yes, in the end you did use מעשר
שני Maaser Sheini *Ma'aser Sheni* money to buy food, although not the
type of food products that we normally approve of or not, you
know, the way etc. But because of that, because it wasn't a
normal purchase, the leather was not...
does the חיה *chayah* for שלמים shelamim *Shlamim* actually work?
So you don't. So what you have to do is you have
to be פודה *podeh* the money and then use the proceeds for
the שלמים shelamim, *Shlamim*, but the amount that you're פודה *podeh* also
includes the value of the עור *or*, not just the value of
the meat.
But do you have to פודה *podeh* for like a fifth more?
That's true as well.
But then you're using unnecessarily מעשר שני maaser sheni. *Ma'aser Sheni* money.
Well, I'm not sure exactly where the fifth is coming from. We'll
see about the fifth, actually the fifth is coming up in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, okay, לא יצא העור לחולין *lo yatza ha'or lechulin*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, לאו למימרא דקני שלמים shelamim, *lav lemeimra
dekani Shlamim*? One minute, so what is it saying? It's saying though
that the leather now, and actually it could have even asked about
the חיה *chayah* itself because that's not the שלמים shelamim *Shlamim*... per
se, the leather does have קדושת שלמים. Kedushas Shlamim. When it says
לא יצא עור לחולין, Lo Yatza Or L'Chullin, what does that mean?
What's the status of the leather? Now this is interesting because you
could have said it means that the status of the leather is
that it has still has קדושת מעשר שני. Kedushas Maaser Sheini. That's
really what we're talking about, the קדושת מעשר שני. Kedushas Maaser Sheini.
When it says for example that the leather does not become desanctified
when it's talking about the בהמה for בשר תאוה, it means that
it has קדושת מעשר שני, Kedushas Maaser Sheini, right? So you could
have said the same by the שלמים, by the case of the
deer for the שלמים. But the גמרא Gemara is assuming that it
means no, that the leather not only has קדושת מעשר שני, Kedushas
Maaser Sheini, it also has קדושת שלמים. Kedusha Shlamim. And therefore you
say, ah, so you see now something which is not actually a
product that's going to be eaten, it's leather. So as leather it's
not something that can be eaten, it's sort of like money of
מעשר שני, maaser sheni and it can have both the קדושת מעשר
שני Kedusha Maaser Sheini and the קדושת שלמים. Kedushas Shlamim. That's the
גמרא's Gemara question. Pretty complicated. So the גמרא Gemara says הא איתמר
עלה אמר רב ha itmar alah amar Rav לא קני שלמים. lo
kani Shlamim. No, no, no, the leather never gets קדושת שלמים. Kedushas
Shlamim. If the leather has קדושת מעשר שני, Kedushas Maaser Sheini, that's
what the משנה mishna, means. But it doesn't mean that it has
קדושת שלמים. Kedushas Shlamim So ומאי לא יצא עור לחולין u-mai lo
yatza or l'chullin and what does it mean that the skin does
not become desanctified? הכי קאמר hachi kamar אינו בתורת להוציא העור לחולין
eino b'toras l'hotzi ha-or l'chullin the skin is not in the category
where it could become desanctified from the מעשר שני maaser sheni status,
meaning מאי טעמא mai taama why? אמר רבא amar Rava נעשה כקוח
שור לחרישה. naaseh k'kocheach shor l'charisha. It's like again, it's like a
complete misuse of מעשר שני maaser sheni funds, like you tried to
use מעשר שני maaser sheni funds to buy an ox for plowing.
So in that type of a case, a complete misuse, we would
not say, oh, well at least you can get the skin and
you don't have to worry. No, if it was a complete misuse,
the whole thing has מעשר שני maaser sheni. sanctity, you have to
redeem the whole thing and you don't have this whole principle of
יצא עור לחולין. yatza or l'chullin. Now again, this is a very
complicated גמרא. Gemara Some read it that actually, I read it that
the whole thing has קדושת מעשר שני Kedushas Maaser Sheini and you
don't get the leather as a benefit like you do in other
cases.
Right, the way the רמב"ם Rambam and others read it is it
means that it doesn't become קדוש kadosh at all. The whole sale
was void and that actually nothing had קדושת מעשר שני. Kedushas Maaser
Sheini. Anyway, it is complicated, but the simple answer though is the
whole question was that they thought that the skin both in this
case both had מעשר שני maaser sheni קדושה Kedusha and שלמים קדושה.
Kedusha. And the real simple answer is we're not talking about שלמים
קדושה. Kedusha. When we say לא יצא העור לחולין we're talking about
the question of that it still has מעשר שני maaser sheni. status,
okay? And we're not saying that it also has שלמים status, that's
not our issue, so you don't have to worry about doubling up.
The reason you read it your way just because this is what
it says?
Yeah, and there are those who read it that way, there are
those who interpret רש"י Rashi that way, okay? And it fits just
better without totally revamping all of our assumptions.
Well I mean, you know, because usually once the כהן Kohen gets
it, or whatever it is, his part of whatever it is, you
know, it's sort of like a common way of saying, you know,
I understand.
Okay, so anyway, so now what do we have? We have first
of all, like I said, there's this interesting side point about מעשר
שני maaser sheni that you get the container or the other attendant
things which don't get קדושת מעשר שני Kedushas Maaser Sheini as long
as it's a normal purchase as opposed to these cases. And we
still have not resolved our issue which is can you give something
that is not actually to be consumed as מעשר שני, maaser sheni.
either money or in this bizarre case the skin, the leather? But
nevertheless, money can have קדושת מעשר שני Kedushas Maaser Sheini and קדושת
שלמים kedushas shelamim. at the same time, and we are arguing now.
So we are going to wrap up with this point. Let's take
a look. איתמר itmar it was taught another debate which was actually
a different variation of this debate: המתפיס מעות מעשר שני לשלמים. hamatpis
ma'os Maaser Sheini l'Shlamim. You are trying to sanctify מעשר שני maaser
sheni money and also add to them שלמים sanctity. המתפיס matpis literally
means to grab, but what it means sort of like to insert
this שלמים sanctity on top of the מעשר שני maaser sheni sanctity.
Same question. But now we're going to sort of see it framed
differently. רבי יוחנן אמר קני Rabbi Yochanan amar kani again a funny
phrase to purchase or to
own, but anyway yes the שלמים sanctity takes effect. רבי אלעזר אמר
לא קני Rabbi Elazar amar lo kani it does not. ואליבא דרבי
יהודה v'aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda now we're going to hear it framed. According
to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda דאמר מעשר ממון הדיוט הוא d'amar Maaser
mamon hedyot hu דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דקני. d'kuly alma lo pligi
d'kani. So there's an interesting debate, a classic debate in ש"ס Shas
between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. How do
you think about מעשר שני? maaser sheni On the one hand מעשר
שני maaser sheni. has requirements, you know, it's considered sanctified, you can
only eat it in ירושלים, you're supposed to do certain things with
it, you can transfer the קדושה Kedusha to money, it has קדושה.
Kedusha. So on the other hand, who eats it? You eat it.
So here's the question, is it considered your money or the בית
המקדש's Beis HaMikdash money? ממון הדיוט mamon hedyot or ממון גבוה? mamon
gavoah? Now again, this really points to two concepts of קדושה Kedusha
which I mentioned a number of times. One concept of קדושה Kedusha
is really a question of ownership, like if I sanctify my car
to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash then when we say it's קדוש,
kadosh, it's קדוש kadosh but it fundamentally emerges from the fact that
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash owns it. I've transferred ownership. When I
sanctify my animal as a קרבן korban so it's not about I've
given it to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it's my animal but
I've given it some, I've defined its status, you know, to have
sanctity. It starts with the קדושה Kedusha idea, not with the ownership
idea, and therefore there are ways in which we could still say
it's mine. So For example by a קרבן korban we have רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili who
says קדשים קלים kodshim kalim is ממון בעלים, mamon ba'alim, it's mine,
especially because in the end I'm going to eat it. Maybe if
I'm not going to eat it it's קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, I
can't say so much it's mine. So you have a very similar
issue by מעשר שני. maaser sheni It starts by קדושה kedusha which
defines its status and what you do with it and so on,
but it's not fundamentally a question of it's owned by the temple.
You're going to take it, you're going to eat it, you're going
to transfer the קדושה kedusha to your money or whatever you're going
to do. So therefore רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's ממון הדיוט,
mamon hedyot, whereas רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says no, in the end
of the day because your ability to use it is very restricted,
it's not like it's really fully yours. So for example, one question
for this would be, can I take my—always the fun question the
גמרא Gemara asks about to determine ownership is the litmus test: can
I marry a woman with it? So can I take my מעשר
שני maaser sheni and say to a woman הרי את מקודשת לי?
harei at mekudeshet li? Now she can go ahead and take this
food and eat it and whatever, you know, I mean she has
use out of it, but is it my money so I've given
her something of mine that is of value or not? So that's
the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda versus רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
So now what we're saying is this: if you say like רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that it's your money, so if it's yours, you
should be able to give it a sanctity of קדושת שלמים. kedushas
shelamim, If it's yours you can use it how you want to.
Now of course that's not necessarily true, it could be yours but
its קדושה kedusha could limit its ability to get another קדושה, kedusha,
but here that's how we're framing it. So let's take a look.
ואליבא דרבי יהודה דאמר מעשר ממון הדיוט הוא, V'aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda d'amar
maaser mamon hedyot hu, according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says
מעשר maaser is lay money, your money essentially, דכולי עלמא לא פליגי
דקני. dkuli alma lo pligi d'kani. Everybody agrees you can sanctify it
with the קדושה kedusha of a שלמים. Now again, that's not necessarily
true, you might have, you know, sort of the property rights to
it, but it doesn't mean that you can totally define its uses,
but nevertheless that's what we're saying. כי פליגי אליבא דרבי מאיר, Ki
pligi aliba d'Rabbi Meir, they debate according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
דאמר מעשר ממון גבוה הוא, d'amar maaser mamon gavoah hu, that actually
is sort of God's money. מאן דאמר לא קני, Man d'amar lo
kani, that it did not become sanctified with קדושת שלמים, kedushas shelamim
is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says,
you know, if it's not your property then you can't sanctify it.
ומאן דאמר קני, U'man d'amar kani, and the one who said it
did
acquire, כיון דמעשר קרי ליה שלמים—or keivan d'maaser kari lei shelamim some
say rather than קרי, kari, some switch the גרסא girsa to
קרב שלמים—because karev shelamim מעשר maaser. is brought as a שלמים, which
is the better even way of reading it, or you know is
naturally used to purchase שלמים, so כי מתפיס ליה נמי תפיס, ki
mafis lei nami tapis, even if it's not your money, by giving
it this קדושה kedusha you're really not sort of taking possession of
it and control of it, you're really sort of almost directing it
towards a natural way in which it would be used, so that's
not a contradiction. Okay, I like that too, except I don't understand
at all why the גמרא Gemara is speaking about it within רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. I mean I would have naturally thought let's have
that discussion within רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. To make it, to give
it קדושת שלמים I would say you need two things. Number one
is you need the property ownership to have the ability to do
it. And number two is you need to address the problem of
the conflict of the קדושות, kedushas, which is what this last point
is doing. But the גמרא Gemara is saying once you've addressed the
conflict of the קדושה kedusha problems, you can do it even if
it's not considered your money. Look, let's face it, in the end,
even if you don't call it your money, you're going to take
it, you're going to use it to buy your things and you're
going to eat it. It's not like anybody can come and grab
your מעשר שני maaser sheni money and say oh it's not yours
I'm going to take it, right? So you're saying it should be
in general a question within רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, what it means
really ממון גבוה, mamon gavoah, because obviously you have the right to
restrict its use and to prevent other people from using it and
you're the one who controls how it gets used.
So you're saying is even within רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda should we
still suspect that it works?
Correct, that is what I'm saying, because even if it's ממון הדיוט
mamon hedyot it doesn't mean that you have no restrictions, right? So
that means they both agree that you have restrict—look, both רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda agree that you're the only
one who's allowed to use it unless you choose to give it
to somebody else, right? And they both agree that there are restrictions
on how you use it and there's a קדושה kedusha defining how
you use it. So to exactly determine you know what they're debating
with ממון גבוה mamon gavoah and ממון הדיוט mamon hedyot requires a
much bigger analysis. Okay, let's wrap this up. Okay,
מתיבי, maysiv, I'll ask you on this. המתפיס מעות מעשר שני לשלמים,
Ha'mafhis maos maaser sheni l'shelamim,
so here is a ברייתא braisa that directly assumes you can do
this. You sanctify מעשר שני maaser sheni money with קדושה kedusha of
שלמים. כשהפודן, Kshe'podan,
there you go Michael, you're redeeming it, מוסיף עליהם שני חומשים. mosif
aleihem shnei chumashim.
So you redeem this money now to be using this, you know,
to be using this to act as a fund that you're also
by the way redeeming money. Why don't you just use the money
towards its right purpose? But for whatever reason you're redeeming this money
and you're transferring it to other money. So then you have to
add two חומשים, chumashim, אחד לקודש ואחד למעשר, echad l'kodesh v'echad l'maaser,
one when you redeem מעשר שני maaser sheni you add a fifth,
and the other when you redeem קודש kodesh you add a fifth.
Now so anyway so there you see that it assumes that you
can be מתפיס mafhis money for מעשר שני.
maaser sheni It's not including the fifth, right? Just the fifth. What?
One fifth doesn't go on top of that.
No, no, no. Anyway, it's parallel. No, no. Anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says, so you see that you can be מתפיס, mafhis, and
you said according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir there was an opinion
that you can't be מתפיס. mafhis. So the גמרא Gemara says, מי
סברת דבעל כרחו, mi savas d'be'al korcho, who said it's against his
will? Who said that that was a unanimous ברייתא? braita? הא מני?
Ha mani? Rabbi Yehuda. That's Rabbi Yehuda. We already said according to
Rabbi Yehuda that it's ממון הדיוט, mammon hedyot, you can be מתפיס,
mafpis, so if you find somebody who says you can be מתפיס,
mafpis, it doesn't prove anything. Now I should add that this is
a very
surprising statement in general because we have never heard before that when
you redeem קרבן korban sanctity you add a fifth. The Torah speaks
about adding a fifth when you redeem מעשר. maaser. It never says
that if I sanctify, let's say I sanctify, I don't know, this
pile of gold for an עולה, olah, and then for whatever reason
I want to use the you know my silver money for the
עולה, olah, I mean it's very bizarre that you're redeeming money for
money but okay whatever anyway, and I'm transferring it to the other
money, we never heard you have to add a fifth when it's
a קרבן korban sanctity, we never find this. If you look at
this little תוספות, Tosfos, מוסיף שני חומשים כאן משמע שיש חומש כשפודה
שלמים וקשה דפרק הזהב משמע דליכא חומש דאמר מה
בהמה מיוחדת וכולי וכולי וכולו
שמעי וכולי וכולי,
Mosif shnei chumashim kan mashma she-yesh chomesh
keshepodeh shelamim ve-kasheh de-perek ha-zahav mashma de-leika chomesh de-amar mah beheimah meyuchadet
etcetera etcetera ve-chulu shmai etcetera etcetera,
okay? So it's a real question whether you would ever add a
fifth when you're redeeming money for a קרבן. korban. This is really
the only time we find that, normally you find it by מעשר.
maaser Okay, now we turn our discussion about not using the money,
you can stipulate otherwise, but as a general rule, although you use
מעשר שני maaser sheni money for שלמים and a תודה, todah, that's
not when you have an obligation. You cannot use it to exempt
you from your to satisfy an obligation. So now that's the point
that this משנה Mishnah turns to.
Meaning you said הרי זו Harei zu versus הרי עלי. Harei alai.
הרי זו Harei zu you can say, הרי עלי Harei alai you
can't, unless you stipulate otherwise, which was the previous משנה. Mishnah And
this משנה now turns it into the general principle. מנין לאומר הרי
עלי תודה שלא יביא אלא מן החולין? Minayin le-omer harei alai todah
shelo yavi ela min hachullin? How do you know this idea we
said in the previous משנה, if somebody says I have to bring
a תודה, todah, that you can only bring from
non-sanctified funds? תלמוד לומר וזבחת פסח לה' אלוהיך צאן ובקר. Talmud lomar
vezavachta pesach l'Hashem Elokecha tzon uvakar. You shall slaughter a פסח pesach
to Hashem your God, sheep and cattle. One of the most difficult
פסוקים psukim הלכתית halachically in the Torah because פסח pesach doesn't come
from cattle. והלא פסח אין בא אלא מן הכבשים ומן העזים, Ve-halo
pesach ein ba ela min hakvasim umin ha-izim, it only comes from
the sheep and the
goats. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר צאן ובקר, Im ken mah talmud
lomar tzon uvakar, sheep and cattle? להקיש כל הבא מן הצאן ומן
הבקר לפסח, Lehakish kol haba min hatzon umin habakar lepesach, to tell
you any type of a thing that you would bring from sheep
and cattle, any קרבן, korban, is just like a פסח. pesach. So
it says וזבחת פסח לה' אלוהיך צאן ובקר, vezavachta pesach l'Hashem Elokecha
tzon uvakar, what it really means is you shall slaughter פסח, pesach,
and similarly any type of קרבן korban you would bring from any
type of an animal is just like this פסח. pesach. Okay, I
don't know if that's exact פשט pshat but all right, להקיש כל
הבא מן הצאן ומן הבקר לפסח. lehakish kol haba min hatzon umin
habakar lepesach. Probably the best, I mean there's no good פשט, pshat,
but the best reconciliation is that the צאן ובקר tzon uvakar refers
to the שלמים that come with the פסח. pesach. So that at
least you can maybe fit into the פסוק וזבחת פסח לה' אלוהיך,
pasuk vezavachta pesach l'Hashem Elokecha, you know, together with צאן ובקר tzon
uvakar that you're bringing at the same time. Anyway, here we're linking
all קרבנות korbanot to
פסח. pesach. מה פסח דבר שבחובה ואין בא אלא מן החולין, Mah
pesach davar shebe-chovah ve-ein ba ela min hachullin, the same way פסח
pesach is an obligation and we know already, the גמרא Gemara is
going to say how do we know already, but we know already
that a פסח pesach can only come from non-sanctified funds. אף כל
דבר שבחובה, Af kol davar shebe-chovah, so we link it to all
קרבנות, korbanot, similarly by all קרבנות korbanot which are an obligation, אין
בא אלא מן החולין, ein ba ela min hachullin, can only come
from non-sanctified funds. לפיכך האומר הרי עלי תודה הרי עלי שלמים, Lefichach
ha-omer harei alai todah harei alai shelamim, and therefore if you obligate
yourself in a תודה todah or שלמים, והואיל ובאו חובה, ve-ho'il uvau
chovah, now they have become an obligation, לא יביאו אלא מן החולין,
lo yavi'u ela min hachullin, you can only bring them from non-sanctified
funds, from non-מעשר שני. maaser sheni ונסכים, Ve-nesachim, and when it comes
to the נסכים, nesachim, בכל מקום לא יביאו אלא מן החולין, bechol
makom lo yavi'u ela min hachullin, can only come from חולין chullin
even if you are not making it an obligation. Why? Because נסכים
nesachim never get eaten by the owners. נסכים, nesachim, if you donate
נסכים, nesachim, whether they're the נסכים nesachim that come with a קרבן,
korban, whether you donate straight נסכים, nesachim, they get poured on the
מזבח, mizbeach, nobody eats them. So you're trying to use your מעשר
שני maaser sheni money, right, that's what we mean חולין chullin in
contrast to מעשר שני. maaser sheni Obviously you can't use other types
of funds because it would be a contradiction. Meaning if I was
מקדיש, makdish, let's say my money to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
there's no question that I can't use it for my קרבן, korban,
right, the money is supposed to go to the temple treasury. The
question is מעשר שני maaser sheni funds. מעשר שני funds I'm allowed
to use to eat. So there there's a question, can I use
מעשר שני funds for קרבנות? korbanot? Okay, so here what we're saying
is one set of קרבנות korbanot you definitely cannot use them for
are קרבנות korbanot that you're not going to eat. So it gives
נסכים nesachim as an example. It could have easily have given an
עולה olah as an example, okay, but maybe it feels like a
נסכים nesachim is less of a big deal, whatever it is. Things
you're not going to eat, totally non-off, because that's a contradiction to
the מעשר שני. But to use it for things you will eat,
that you can use מעשר שני for, you can use it for
שלמים, you can use it for תודה, todah, but just don't use
it if you have an obligation. If you have an obligation you
can't use it for things that you're already obligated.
And why can't you use it for something that somebody else eats?
What? Why can't you use it for something that somebody else eats
but not you?
You mean like a חטאת? chatas? Because that's an obligation, that wouldn't
be a good example. What thing, a מנחה mincha would be a
good example. Okay, a
מנחה. mincha. You know it's so in
theory it's interesting it seems to be that you know you should
be eating and
happy you could also give to other people right that's the פסוק
pasuk of והלוי אשר בשעריך v'halevi asher bisharecha you share so you're
sharing with the כהנים Kohanim
although they could eat it right although theoretically they could eat it
yeah the question is I don't know the question is about the
burning of let's say the קומץ kometz of the מנחה minchah would
that be a challenge would that be a problem but I don't
know the מנחה minchah is certainly a definite possibility
I mean look at the little תוספות Tosfos by the way להקיש
דבר הבא מן הצאן ומן הבקר l'hakish davar haba min hatzon umin
habakar תוספות Tosfos says here תימא תינח זבחים עופות ומנחות ולחמי תודה
מנלן Teima teinach zvachim ofos u'menachos u'lachmei todah minalan okay
so how do we know that this rule applies to things that
are not קרבנות korbanot because you learn it from צאן ובקר tzon
u'bakar and presumably it does apply to other קרבנות korbanot as well
that you can't be בא מן החובה ba min hachovah but in
terms of your question it would seem to me I'd have to
check but off the top of my head I would say you
could bring a מנחה minchah from the from מעשר שני and let
the כהן Kohen eat the מנחה minchah although you still have to
deal with the fact that nobody is eating the קומץ kometz okay
let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara. ופסח גופיה מנלן U'pesach
gufei minalan
so this משנה assumed that it's for granted that a פסח Pesach
can only come from a חולין chullin how do we know that
דתניא De'tanya we learned in a ברייתא Braisa רבי אליעזר אומר Rebbi
Eliezer omer נאמר פסח במצרים ונאמר פסח לדורות Neemar Pesach b'Mitzrayim v'neemar
Pesach l'doros
we have the פסח מצרים Pesach Mitzrayim and we have the general
פסח Pesach wait
what was the question ופסח גופיה מנלן Pesach gufei minalan how
do you know that a פסח Pesach can only come from a
חולין chullin the משנה said since it's true for פסח Pesach therefore
we apply to other things how do you know from פסח Pesach
maybe you can make bring a פסח Pesach from מעשר שני money
it's a type of a שלמים essentially bring it from מעשר שני
money so רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says no we have פסח מצרים
Pesach Mitzrayim and we have the פסח Pesach for later generations מה
פסח האמור במצרים לא בא אלא מן החולין Mah Pesach hamur b'Mitzrayim
lo ba ela min hachullin the same way the one in מצרים
Mitzrayim did not come from מעשר שני money how do you know
first of all they hadn't been commanded מעשר שני yet second of
all מעשר שני is only for grain that grew in Israel not
grain that grew in Egypt okay so the same way the פסח
Pesach in מצרים Mitzrayim did not come from מעשר שני money אלא
מן החולין ela min hachullin אף פסח האמור לדורות לא בא אלא
מן החולין af Pesach hamur l'doros lo ba ela min hachullin the
same for the one for generations אמר ליה רבי עקיבא Amar leh
Rebbi Akiva וכי דנין אפשר משאי
אפשר v'chi danin efshar mishe'ee efshar
can you learn out the case where it was possible from where
it was impossible you didn't have a choice so you can't learn
from the fact that they didn't bring it from that money there
was not even a possibility to have brought it from that money
אמר ליה Amar leh so רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer said back to
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva אף על פי שאי אפשר af al pi
she'ee efshar although it was impossible ראיה גדולה היא raya gedolah hee
I still think it's a big proof that's what you say ונילמד
ממנו u'nimad mimenu we can learn from it that since it only
came from חולין chullin that's true by all קרבן פסחs Korban Pesach
okay חזר רבי עקיבא ודן דין אחר hazar Rebbi Akiva v'dan din
acher רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva went back and tried to attack him
again
מה לפסח מצרים שכן אין טעון מתן דמים ואימורים לגבי מזבח mah
l'Pesach Mitzrayim shekein ein teun matan damim v'eimurim legabei mizbeiach you never
had blood
on the מזבח mizbeiach you never had I mean they had it
on the doorpost but not on the מזבח mizbeiach you didn't have
you know the burning of the אימורים eimurim so you can't learn
it תאמר בפסח לדורות tomar b'Pesach l'doros how can you apply what
was true there even ignoring the fact that it was אי אפשר
ee efshar how can you apply it to the פסח Pesach of
later generations שטעון מתן
דמים ואימורים לגבי מזבח sheteun matan damim v'eimurim legabei mizbeiach that you
put the blood and the אימורים eimurim on the מזבח mizbeiach and
maybe it has different rules although since maybe you'd say that that's
a higher standard but nevertheless it's a different standard and therefore you
can't apply from one to the other אמר לו amar lo so
he said back to him רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer said back to
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva הרי הוא אומר harei hu omer ועבדת את
העבודה הזאת בחדש הזה v'avadta es ha'avodah hazos bachodesh hazeh right
and the famous thing your child will ask you what is you
know in the future generations and you will do this service you
know in this month referring to the later קרבן פסחs Korban Pesach
but this was a פסוק pasuk given when they were bringing the
פסח מצרים Pesach Mitzrayim שכל עבודת החדש הזה כזה shekol avodas hachodesh
hazeh kazeh
so the תורה Torah is telling you all future קרבן פסחs Korban
Pesach will follow the standards of the first פסח Pesach so since
the first פסח Pesach again was not was only בא מן החולין
ba min hachullin you didn't use מעשר money the same is true
by later פסח Pesach ורבי עקיבא v'Rebbi Akiva so the גמרא says
and רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva let me get this straight אי סבר
לה דאין דנין אפשר משאי אפשר ie savar lah de'ein danin efshar
mishe'ee efshar if he holds you can fundamentally not learn out you
know possible from the not possible ליקם במילתיה laigei b'milsai so let
him keep you know stick by your position why are you now
trying another argument you know stick by your position אי הדר ביה
ie hadar beh
and if he's reversed his position changed his mind and said maybe
you can learn out from אי אפשר ee efshar והאי דלא גמר
מפסח מצרים משום האי פירכא הוא v'hai d'lo gamar me'Pesach Mitzrayim mishum
hai pircha hu
and the only reason now that he's not learning out from פסח
מצרים Pesach Mitzrayim is not that it's אי אפשר ee efshar but
because of this issue about it wasn't put on the מזבח mizbeiach
תדון tzeden then his position doesn't make sense פסח מדבר יוכיח Pesach
Midbar yochiach then there was other פסחים psachim there's the פסח Pesach
they brought in the מדבר Midbar which we're going to read about
very soon that was put the blood on the מזבח mizbeiach and
that's another good example for רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer why cuz that
the blood went on the מזבח mizbeiach and the אימורים eimurim but
it also didn't come from מעשר שני money how do you know
it didn't come from מעשר שני money cuz they're not giving מעשר
שני from grain that they're growing in the מדבר Midbar okay so
the גמרא is saying like this if you want to hold by
your position you can't
learn
out from
אי אפשר ee efshar we understand don't learn out from
any It's kind of obvious.
So the גמרא says לדבריו דרבי אליעזר קאמר. l'divrav d'Rabbi Eliezer ka'amar.
He's saying back according to within רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer's position. לדידי,
L'didi, as far as I'm concerned, says רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, אין
דנים אפשר משאי אפשר. ein dnim efshar mish'ee efshar. You can't learn
a case where it's possible from a case where it's not possible.
Both מצרים Mitzrayim and the מדבר midbar are irrelevant. לדידך, L'didach, according
to you, דאמרת דנים אפשר משאי אפשר, d'amart dnim efshar mish'ee efshar,
you're prepared to
learn from the possible from the not possible, and you want to
learn from פסח מצרים. Pesach Mitzrayim. So according to you,
מה לפסח מצרים שכן אין טעון מתן דמים ואימורים לגבי מזבח, mah
l'Pesach Mitzrayim sheken ein taun matan damim v'emurim l'gabei mizbeach, תאמר בפסח
דורות שטעון מתן דמים ואימורים לגבי מזבח. tomar b'Pesach dorot shetaun matan
damim v'emurim l'gabei mizbeach. How can you learn from פסח מצרים Pesach
Mitzrayim where there was no altar to the פסח דורות? Pesach dorot?
So of course that is a still, it doesn't really solve the
problem, because it's still like as we would say, excuse me, a
קלוץ קשיא, klotz kashya, because even with לדידך l'didach of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer that learns אפשר משאי אפשר, efshar mish'ee efshar, okay, so
you've disproven פסח מצרים. Pesach Mitzrayim. I'll still tell you פסח מדבר,
Pesach midbar, right? So who cares? Meaning, even if it's even if
we understand why רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva has not gone over to
רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer's side, we don't understand the strength of the
question. The question only undermined the פסח מצרים Pesach Mitzrayim argument; it
didn't undermine, just shifted to a פסח דורות Pesach dorot argument. Okay,
now we'll just finish this point.
ועבדת. V'avadta. ואמר ליה רבי אליעזר, V'amar lei Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer said back to him, ועבדת, v'avadta, I'm going to have
a פסוק pasuk that's going to link פסח מצרים Pesach Mitzrayim to
all future פסח דורות. Pesach dorot. So now the גמרא says, so
I don't understand why רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer jumped there. רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, לימא ליה, leima lei, why didn't רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
say back to him, פסח מדבר יוכיח, Pesach midbar yochiach, exactly what
we just said? Why did רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer have to go
to a פסוק pasuk of ועבדת? v'avadta? Why not say to him,
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, don't give me a hard time about פסח
מצרים, Pesach Mitzrayim, I'll just learn from
פסח מדבר? Pesach midbar? What difference does it make? So the גמרא
says, same point. לדבריו דרבי עקיבא קאמר ליה. L'divrav d'Rabbi Akiva ka'amar
lei. He's saying back to use this to contradict רבי עקיבא's Rabbi
Akiva's own position. לדידי, L'didi, as far as I'm concerned, where I
hold דנים אפשר משאי אפשר, dnim efshar mish'ee efshar, I can learn
from the possible from the not possible, ומשום האי פירכא, u'mishum hai
pircha, and that you're bothered that פסח מצרים Pesach Mitzrayim didn't have
a מזבח, mizbeach, that was the question you wanted to challenge my
own position on. That doesn't bother me. פסח מדבר יוכיח. Pesach midbar
yochiach. I'll just shift from פסח מצרים Pesach Mitzrayim to פסח מדבר.
Pesach midbar. I still, I'm not bothered by your question, רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. But I'm going to go one step further, not just
answer your question, I'm going to attack you on your own grounds.
I'm going to say לדידך, l'didach, even according to you, דאמרת אין
דנים אפשר משאי אפשר, d'amart ein dnim efshar mish'ee efshar, you don't
want to learn out from פסח מדבר Pesach midbar and פסח מצרים
Pesach Mitzrayim because those were אי אפשר, ee efshar, I'm going to
attack that. Why? ועבדת. V'avadta.
I've got a פסוק pasuk that links them. It says ועבדת העבודה
הזאת, v'avadta ha'avoda ha'zot, so this פסוק pasuk, links them and therefore
you should be forced to admit that you do use this as
the standard. So the גמרא says, והשתא נמי לפרוך, v'hashta nami lifroch,
so what you have a פסוק, pasuk still say it's אפשר efshar
and אי אפשר, ee efshar, you can't learn one from the other.
אמר רב ששת, amar Rav Sheshet, זאת אומרת, zot omeret, this tells
you, אין משיבין על ההיקש. ein meshivin al ha'heikesh. This tells you
that once you have a פסוק pasuk that explicitly links them, you
no longer ask any questions. If the פסוק pasuk is almost like
a גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, if the פסוק pasuk is saying A
is like B and the laws of A apply to B, the
fact I could say, oh, but it's different this way and it's
different that way, that's irrelevant. אין משיבין על ההיקש, Ein meshivin al
ha'heikesh, that's a famous line that is used many times in the
גמרא. You can see by the asterisk where sort of a couple
of places where בבא קמא Bava Kamma has the whole list. Anyway,
so that's what we say. So רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer's response to
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is, don't give me a hard time, אפשר
efshar and אי אפשר. ee efshar. Or even according to you that
you're bothered by it, the פסוק explicitly links them. And once it
explicitly links them, your questions now become irrelevant. Okay, we continue tomorrow.